Renan Souza

Bio

Renan Francisco Santos Souza holds a Ph.D. (2019) and an M.Sc. (2015) in Computer Science from COPPE/Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), and a B.Sc. in Computer Science from UFRJ (2009-2013). Since 2015, he works at IBM Research Brazil, where he is a Research Scientist in the Industrial Cloud Technologies group. He has been working both as a software engineer and a researcher in several projects since 2010 and has been actively publishing scientific papers in refereed international conferences and journals since 2014. During his B.Sc., he spent a school year at Missouri State University and did a summer internship at Stanford University in the SLAC National Laboratory. During his Ph.D., he was a visiting researcher at Inria/Univ. Montpellier in France in 2019. In 2017, he won the best M.Sc. thesis award from SBBD, the main conference on data management in Latin America. He researches large-scale data science and engineering techniques for the support of Artificial Intelligence systems.

Research Interests

Large-scale Data Science and Engineering • Parallel Workflows • Data Provenance • Big Data Analytics • High Performance Computing in Clusters and Clouds • Machine Learning •

Education

- o Ph.D. in Computer Science, Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
 Supervised by Marta Mattoso and Patrick Valduriez
 Title: Supporting User Steering in Large-scale Workflows with Provenance Data
- o Visiting Ph.D. Student, Inria/Univ. Montpellier, France Jan 2019 Mar 2019 Supervised by Patrick Valduriez
- M.Sc. in Computer Science, Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Jan 2013 Jul 2015
 Supervised by Marta Mattoso
 Title: Controlling the Parallel Execution of Workflows Relying on a Distributed Database
- o Computer Science exchange student, Missouri State University, U.S. Jun 2011 Jun 2012
- o B.Sc. in Computer Science, Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Jan 2009 Dec 2012 Supervised by Maria Luiza Machado Campos

Title: Linked Open Data Publication Strategies: An Application in Network Performance Data (in pt)

o Technical Degree in Information Systems, Lemos de Castro Jan 2005 – Dec 2007

Experience

o IBM Research, Research Scientist	Aug 2019 – present
o IBM Research, Research Engineer	Sep 2015 – Aug 2019
o IBM Research, Software Engineer Intern	Apr 2015 - Sep 2015
o Stanford Univeristy, SLAC, Research Collaborator	Aug 2013 - Dec 2014
 Stanford University, SLAC, Research Intern 	May 2013 - Aug 2013
o CAPGov - Government Technologies, Leading Software Engineer	Dec 2013 - Sep 2014

o CAPGov - Government Technologies, Software Engineer

Sep 2013 – Jan 2014

o CAPGov - Government Technologies, Software Engineer Intern

Jan 2011 - Jun 2012

o Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro, Software Engineer Intern

Jan 2010 - Jul 2011

Selected Publications

For complete list, visit: RenanSouza.org/publications

- [1] R. Souza, L. Azevedo, V. Lourenço, E. Soares, R. Thiago, R. Brandão, D. Civitarese, E. Vital Brazil, M. Moreno, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, R. Cerqueira, M. A. S. Netto, "Provenance data in the machine learning lifecycle in computational science and engineering," in Workflows in Support of Large-Scale Science (WORKS) co-located with the ACM/IEEE International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC), 2019, pp. 1–10. DOI: 10.1109/WORKS49585.2019.00006. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.04223.
- [2] R. Souza, L. Azevedo, R. Thiago, E. Soares, M. Nery, M. Netto, E. V. Brazil, R. Cerqueira, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Efficient runtime capture of multiworkflow data using provenance," in *IEEE International Conference on e-Science (eScience)*, 2019, pp. 1–10. DOI: 10.1109/eScience.2019.00047. [Online]. Available: https://hal-lirmm.ccsd.cnrs.fr/lirmm-02265932.
- [3] R. Souza, V. Silva, J. J. Camata, A. L. G. A. Coutinho, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Keeping track of user steering actions in dynamic workflows," *Future Generation Computer Systems*, vol. 99, pp. 624–643, 2019, ISSN: 0167-739X. DOI: 10.1016/j.future.2019.05.011. [Online]. Available: https://hal-lirmm.ccsd.cnrs.fr/lirmm-02127456.
- [4] R. Souza, V. Silva, A. L. G. A. Coutinho, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Data reduction in scientific workflows using provenance monitoring and user steering," *Future Generation Computer Systems*, vol. online, pp. 1–34, 2017, ISSN: 0167-739X. DOI: 10.1016/j.future.2017.11.028. [Online]. Available: https://hal-lirmm.ccsd.cnrs.fr/lirmm-01679967/document.

Technical Knowledge

- o Languagess: Python, Java, C, C++, Shell scripting, NodeJS, Scala, Lua
- Relational DBMS: PostgreSQL/PostGIS, DB2, DashDB, MySQL, MySQL Cluster, MS SQL Server
- o **NoSQL DBMS**: MongoDB, AllegroGraph, Jena, Virtuoso, Sesame, Cloudant, CouchBase, Redis, Impala, Elasticsearch, HBase, Hive, Apache Ignite
- Heterogeneous Data Management : Data Integration, Multi-database Queries, Polystores, Foreign Data Wrappers
- Big Data Frameworks : Apache Spark: RDD, DataFrames, Streaming, MLib, GraphX, Graph-Frames; Hadoop Ecosystem
- Message Brokers : Kafka, RabbitMQ
- Data Science/ML Technologies: Pandas DataFrames, Jupyter, Numpy, SciPy, Tensorflow, and PyTorch
- o Big Data Cluster Deployment : YARN, Mesos, Standalone deployment
- o Business Intelligence : MS SQL Server BI developer studio, Pentaho Solutions, Talend;
- o Semantic Web Tools/Languages: OWL, RDF, SPARQL, Protege
- **Distributed and Concurrent Programming** : MPI, OpenMP, CUDA, Data-centric distributed and parallel programming
- Cloud and Cluster computing: VMs, Dockers, Kubernetes, HPC Clusters
- o DevOps: Containers, Kubernetes, OpenShift, CI/CD Pipelines, GitHub, Travis, Jenkins
- Domain-specific knowledge: Techniques to analyze large amounts of geological data (SEG-Y, Well logs), OpendTect
- Web Development: Python Flask/UWSGI, Java EE: JSP, JSF, JPA, Hibernate, Tomcat/JBoss

Languages o English - Full proficiency Missouri State University, U.S. Jun 2012 - Aug 2012 (150h) Scientific English for Graduate Students o Cultura Inglesa (English Culture), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil 2001 - 2009o Portuguese - Native o Spanish - Fluent reading, intermediate speaking and understanding, limited writing **Grants & Awards** o SBBD Best M.Sc. Thesis Award 2017 Honored Mention at SBBD on the paper Spark Scalability Analysis in a Scientific Workflow 2017 CAPES M.Sc. Grant 2013 - 2014o Brazil Science Mobility Grant - Missouri State University 2012 - 2013o Scientific Initiation Grant - Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro 2010 **Teaching and Supervisions Teaching:** Databases Laboratory, graduate, UFRJ 2017 Teacher assistant to Prof. Marta Mattoso o Logics for Computer Science, undergraduate, UFRJ 2012-2013 Teacher assistant to Prof. Mario Benevides **Supervisions of final dissertations** Pedro Paiva Miranda, undergraduate, UFRJ, Co-supervision with Prof. Marta Mattoso
 2015 Thesis title: A Mechanism for Fault Tolerance in Parallel Executions of Workflows supported by a Database o Pedro Paiva Miranda, undergraduate, UFRJ, Co-supervision with Prof. Marta Mattoso 2015 Thesis title: Publication of Workflows Provenance Data in the Semantic Web Talks and Events Participation

0	Open Subsurface Data Universe Development Workshop in Houston, TX	2020
0	IEEE/ACM Supercomputing (SC) in Denver, CO	2019
	Workflows in Support of Large-scale Science (WORKS)	
	 Provenance Data in the Machine Learning Lifecycle in Computational Science and Engineering presentation 	g, Oral
0	SciDISC Workhsop in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil	2019
	 Provenance Data in the Machine Learning Lifecycle in Computational Science and Engineering presentation 	g, Oral
0	Open Subsurface Data Universe F2F Meeting in Houston, TX	2019
0	IEEE International Conference on e-Science in San Diego, CA	2019
	- Efficient Runtime Capture of Multiworkflow Data using Provenance, Oral presentation	
0	INRIA Talks in Montpellier, France	2019
	 Providing Online Data Analytical Support for Humans in the Loop of Computational Science Engineering Applications, Oral presentation 	ce and
0	IBM Regional Technical Exchange in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil	2019
0	Provenance Week in London, UK	2018
	International Provenance and Annotation Workshop (IPAW)	

- Provenance of Dynamic Adaptations in User-steered Dataflows, Oral presentation
- Capturing Provenance for Runtime Data Analysis in Computational Science and Engineering Applications, Poster presentation

Computational Reproducibility Workshop

- Provenance of Dynamic Adaptations in User-steered Dataflows, Oral presentation
- International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB) in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil 2018
 Latin American Data Science Workshop
 - Tracking Hyperparameter Tuning in Deep Learning Training, Oral presentation
- o SBC Brazilian Syposium on Databases (SBBD) in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
- o SBC Brazilian Syposium on Databases (SBBD) in Uberlandia, Brazil 2017
 - Spark Scalability Analysis in a Scientific Workflow, Oral presentation
 - Controlling the Parallel Execution of Workflows Relying on a Distributed Database, Oral presentation
- o Federal University of Uberlandia, Brazil in Uberlandia, Brazil

2017

2018

- Kubernetes, Invited talk
- Hacker at the Smart City Cloud Hackathon OpenStack Rio in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil 2017
- o Computer Science Week at UFRJ in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

2017

- Kubernetes, Oral presentation
- SBC Brazilian Conference on Artificial Intelligence (BRACIS) in Recife, Brazil
 Graph Analytics with Spark, Tutorial , link
- IEEE/ACM Supercomputing (SC) in Salt Lake City, UT Workflows in Support of Large-scale Science (WORKS)

2016

- Online Input Data Reduction in Scientific Workflows, Oral presentation
- ASE BigData/SocialCom/CyberSecurity in Stanford University, Menlo Park, CA

 2014
 - Revise name, poster presentation

All Publications and Patents

Journal Articles....

- [J1] R. Souza, V. Silva, J. J. Camata, A. L. G. A. Coutinho, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Keeping track of user steering actions in dynamic workflows," *Future Generation Computer Systems*, vol. 99, pp. 624–643, 2019, ISSN: 0167-739X. DOI: 10.1016/j.future.2019.05.011. [Online]. Available: https://hal-lirmm.ccsd.cnrs.fr/lirmm-02127456.
- [J2] V. Silva, L. Neves, R. Souza, A. L. G. A. Coutinho, D. Oliveira, M. Mattoso, "Adding domain data to code profiling tools to debug workflow parallel execution," Future Generation Computer Systems, pp. 624–643, 2018, ISSN: 0167-739X. DOI: 10.1016/j.future.2018.05.078. [Online]. Available: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.future.2018.05.078.
- [J3] M. G. Bayser, P. Cavalin, R. Souza, A. Braz, H. Candello, C. Pinhanez, J.-P. Briot, "A hybrid architecture for multi-party conversational systems," arXiv preprint Computation and Language (cs.CL), pp. 1–40, 2017. DOI: arXiv:1705.01214. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.01214.
- [J4] R. Souza, V. Silva, A. L. G. A. Coutinho, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Data reduction in scientific workflows using provenance monitoring and user steering," *Future Generation Computer Systems*, vol. online, pp. 1–34, 2017, ISSN: 0167-739X. DOI: 10.1016/j.future.2017.11.028. [Online]. Available: https://hal-lirmm.ccsd.cnrs.fr/lirmm-01679967/document.

Conference and Workshop Papers.....

- [C1] L. Azevedo, R. Souza, E. Soares, M. Moreno, "Modern federated databases: An overview," in *International Conference on Enterprise Information Systems (ICEIS)*, 2020.
- [C2] L. Azevedo, R. Souza, R. Thiago, E. Soares, M. Moreno, "Experiencing provlake to manage the data lineage of ai workflows," in *Meeting in Innovation in Information Systems (EISI) in Brazilian Symposium in Information Systems (SBSI)*, 2020.

- [C3] R. Souza, J. Camata, M. Mattoso, A. Coutinho, "Runtime steering of parallel cfd simulations," in *International Conference on Parallel Computational Fluid Dynamics*, 2020.
- [C4] R. Souza, A. Codas, J. A. Nogueira Junior, M. P. Quinones, L. Azevedo, R. Thiago, E. Soares, M. Cardoso, L. Martins, "Supporting the training of physics informed neural networks for seismic inversion using provenance," in *American Association of Petroleum Geologists Annual Convention and Exhibition (AAPG)*, 2020.
- [C5] R. Thiago, R. Souza, L. Azevedo, E. Soares, R. Santos, W. Santos, M. De Bayser, M. Cardoso, M. Moreno, R. Cerqueira, "Managing data lineage of O&G machine learning models: The sweet spot for shale use case," in *European Association of Geoscientists and Engineers (EAGE) Digitalization Conference and Exhibition*, 2020.
- [C6] R. Souza, L. Azevedo, V. Lourenço, E. Soares, R. Thiago, R. Brandão, D. Civitarese, E. Vital Brazil, M. Moreno, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, R. Cerqueira, M. A. S. Netto, "Provenance data in the machine learning lifecycle in computational science and engineering," in Workflows in Support of Large-Scale Science (WORKS) co-located with the ACM/IEEE International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC), 2019, pp. 1–10. DOI: 10.1109/WORKS49585.2019.00006. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.04223.
- [C7] R. Souza, L. Azevedo, R. Thiago, E. Soares, M. Nery, M. Netto, E. V. Brazil, R. Cerqueira, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Efficient runtime capture of multiworkflow data using provenance," in *IEEE International Conference on e-Science (eScience)*, 2019, pp. 1–10. DOI: 10.1109/eScience.2019.00047. [Online]. Available: https://hal-lirmm.ccsd.cnrs.fr/lirmm-02265932.
- [C8] R. Souza, E. V. Brazil, L. Azevedo, D. Ferreira, E. Soares, R. Thiago, M. Nery, V. Torres, R. Cerqueira, "Managing data traceability in the data lifecycle for deep learning applied to seismic data," in *American Association of Petroleum Geologists Annual Convention and Exhibition (AAPG)*, 2019. [Online]. Available: www.searchanddiscovery.com/abstracts/html/2019/ace2019/abstracts/1718.html.
- [C9] M. G. Bayser, C. Pinhanez, H. Candello, M. Affonso, M. P. Vasconcelos, M. A. Guerra, P. Cavalin, R. Souza, "Ravel: A mas orchestration platform for human-chatbots conversations," in *The 6th International Workshop on Engineering Multi-Agent Systems (EMAS@AAMAS 2018)*, Stockholm, Sweden, 2018.
- [C10] V. Silva, R. Souza, J. Camata, D. Oliveira, P. Valduriez, A. L. G. A. Coutinho, M. Mattoso, "Capturing provenance for runtime data analysis in computational science and engineering applications," in *Provenance and Annotation of Data and Processes*, ser. Lecture Notes in Computer Science (LNCS), Springer International Publishing, 2018, pp. 183–187, ISBN: 978-3-319-98379-0. [Online]. Available: https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-98379-0.15.
- [C11] R. Souza and M. Mattoso, "Provenance of dynamic adaptations in user-steered dataflows," in *Provenance and Annotation of Data and Processes*, ser. Lecture Notes in Computer Science (LNCS), Springer International Publishing, 2018, pp. 16–29, ISBN: 978-3-319-98379-0. [Online]. Available: https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-98379-0_2.
- [C12] R. Souza, L. Neves, L. Azeredo, R. Luiz, E. Tady, P. Cavalin, M. Mattoso, "Towards a human-in-the-loop library for tracking hyperparameter tuning in deep learning development," in Latin American Data Science (LaDaS) workshop co-located with the Very Large Database (VLDB) conference, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 2018, pp. 84–87. [Online]. Available: http://ceurws.org/Vol-2170/paper12.pdf.
- [C13] R. Souza, V. Silva, J. Camata, A. Coutinho, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Tracking of online parameter fine-tuning in scientific workflows," in *Workflows in Support of Large-Scale Science (WORKS) workshop co-located with the ACM/IEEE International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC)*, Denver, CO, 2017. [Online]. Available: https://hal-lirmm.ccsd.cnrs.fr/lirmm-01620974.
- [C14] R. Souza, V. Silva, P. Miranda, A. A. B. Lima, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Spark scalability analysis in a scientific workflow," in *Simpósio Brasileiro de Banco de Dados (SBBD)*, 2017, pp. 288–293. [Online]. Available: http://sbbd.org.br/2017/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2018/02/p288-293.pdf.

- [C15] T. Barbosa, R. Souza, S. Cruz, M. Campos, R. L. Cottrell, "Applying data warehousing and big data techniques to analyze internet performance," SLAC National Accelerator Lab., Menlo Park, CA (United States), Tech. Rep., 2016.
- [C16] P. Cavalin, F. Figueiredo, M. Bayser, L. Moyano, H. Candello, A. Appel, R. Souza, "Building a question-answering corpus using social media and news articles," in *International Conference on Computational Processing of the Portuguese Language*, 2016, pp. 353–358.
- [C17] V. Silva, L. Neves, R. Souza, A. Coutinho, D. D. Oliveira, M. Mattoso, "Integrating domain-data steering with code-profiling tools to debug data-intensive workflows," in Workflows in Support of Large-Scale Science (WORKS) workshop co-located with the ACM/IEEE International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC), Salt Lake City, USA, 2016.
- [C18] R. Souza, V. Silva, A. Coutinho, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Online input data reduction in scientific workflows," in *Workflows in Support of Large-Scale Science (WORKS) workshop colocated with the ACM/IEEE International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC)*, 2016, pp. 1–10. [Online]. Available: https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/lirmm-01400538.
- [C19] R. Castro, R. Souza, V. Silva, K. Ocaña, D. Oliveira, M. Mattoso, "Uma abordagem para publicação de dados de proveniência de workflows científicos na web semântica," in Simpósio Brasileiro de Banco de Dados (SBBD), 2015.
- [C20] R. Souza, V. Silva, D. Oliveira, P. Valduriez, A. A. B. Lima, M. Mattoso, "Parallel execution of workflows driven by a distributed database management system," in ACM/IEEE International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC), Salt Lake City, USA, 2015, pp. 1–3. [Online]. Available: http://sc15.supercomputing.org/sites/all/themes/SC15images/tech_poster/tech_poster_pages/post284.html.
- [C21] R. Souza, L. Cottrell, B. White, M. L. Campos, M. Mattoso, "Linked open data publication strategies: Application in networking performance measurement data," in ASE Big-Data/SocialCom/CyberSecurity, Stanford, CA, 2014.

Patents

- [P1] A. Braz, P. R. Cavalin, F. Figueiredo, M. G. De Bayser, R. Souza, System and method for managing artificial conversational entities enhanced by social knowledge, Granted, US Patent Application 15/265,615, 2018.
- [P2] M. G. De Bayser, A. Braz, P. R. Cavalin, F. Figueiredo, R. Souza, *Creating coordinated multi-chatbots using natural dialogues by means of knowledge base*, Granted, US Patent Application 15/217,660, 2018.
- [P3] A. P. Appel, A. Gama Leal, R. Souza, *Predicting user question in question and answer system*, Granted, US Patent Application 15/171,055, 2017.